Finding Aid for Museum of Zoology (University of Michigan) records 1876-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Photographs
  - Groups
    - George Reserve 1965 (Box 4)
      (T.H. Hubbell and others)
    - Guatemala expedition 1956 (Box 4)
    - Honolulu meeting 1966 (Box 4)
    - Museum staff May 1938 (football game and picnic) (Box 4)
    - Museum staff October 1938 (Box 4)
      (Baker's field day)
    - Museum staff 1964 (Box 4)
    - Owl catching (Ann Arbor) 1916 (Box 4)
  - Museum Buildings
    - 1880 museum building (later, the Romance Languages building) (Box 4)
    - 1927 University Museums building, circa 1961 (Box 4)
    - Museums building addition, circa 1964 (Box 4)
    - Photograph albums (Box 4)
      - Construction of the University Museums building March 2, 1927-October 10, 1927 (Box 4)
      - Expeditions and miscellaneous 1904-1913 (Box 4)
- Publications
  Publications (0.3 linear feet) contain both museum publications and publications about the museum. This printed material has been divided into three groups: excerpts from the annual reports of the Museum of Zoology, 1907-1933; articles and reprints; and miscellaneous. For the most part, these publications are not duplicated elsewhere at the Bentley Library. Researchers should also consult the printed catalog for additional publications by and about the Museum of Zoology.
  - "Excerpts from Annual Reports of the Museum of Zoology, 1907-1933" 1940, 1 volumes (Box 4)
  - Articles and Reprints
    - Alexander G. Ruthven 1909-1920
      - "The Cold-Blooded Vertebrates of Isle Royale" 1909 supplement to Ann. Rept. Geol. Surv. Mich., 1905 (Box 4)
      - "Notes on Michigan Reptiles and Amphibians, II", Twelfth Report of the Michigan Academy of Science 1910 (Box 4)
      - "Report of the Chief Naturalist", Fourteenth Report of the Michigan Academy of Science 1912 (Box 4)
      - "The Museum of Zoology" The Michigan Alumnus, February, 1918 pp. 310-312 (Box 4)
      - Teachers' Manual to Accompany Principles of Animal Biology, New York: McGraw-Hill, 1920 (Box 4)
    - Museum staff 1906-1944
      - F.S. Hall, "Museum Methods", Ninth Annual Report of the Michigan Academy of Science 1906 (Box 4)
      - "The Need for a New Science Building" University of Michigan Bulletin, new series, vol. 14, no. 11 February, 1913 (Box 4)
      - T. Barbour, "Occasional Papers of the Museum of Zoology, University of Michigan" Science, December, 1917 (Box 4)
      - Carl E. Guthe, "The Museums at Michigan", reprinted from The Michigan Alumnus Quarterly Review, Winter 1937 (Box 4)
      - George R. La Rue, "The Biological Station", reprinted from The University of Michigan-An Encyclopedic Survey, 1944 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous 1903-1976
      - Israel C. Russell, "The Topographic Survey of Michigan", address to the Michigan Academy of Science 1903 (Box 4)
      - Bruce B. Collette and Ernest A. Lachner, "Fish Collections in the United States and Canada", reprinted from Copeia, 1976, no.3, pp. 625-642 (Box 4)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files (2.0 linear feet) are arranged alphabetically and contain documentation of the activity and operation of the Museum of Zoology for a period covering over 60 years. However, the bulk of the material dates from the early 1970s to the late 1980s and emanates from the directorships of Nelson G. Hairston, Donald W. Tinkle, Robert Storer, and William R. Dawson. As in the earlier series, those wishing to gain a historical understanding of the museum and its origin should consult the "Historical" folders. These folders contain writings created by museum faculty and staff that document important events in the museum's past. Another topic that may be of interest to those examining the history of the museum is the "Future of the UMMZ (University of Michigan Museum of Zoology)." This folder contains information on grants and external funds collected by the museum and documents that discuss the future of the museum as well as the field of systematics at the university. There are also several reports contained in this series that highlight the history, achievements, and agenda of the museum, including an October 1994 report from the director and a 1997 special report to Dean Edie N. Goldenberg of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts.
  Information about the directors' and their activity at the Museum can be gleaned from the "Directors' Correspondence" and "Directors' Memos" folders. Additional well-documented activities of the museum include the annual award of the Edwin C. Hinsdale, Edward C. Walker, and E.S. George Reserve Scholarships to outstanding graduate students in the field of zoology; the visiting scientists and professors programs which bring distinguished individuals to the museum for a period of one week (scientist) or one term (professors) to conduct research and offer seminars and courses; and the care and handling of live vertebrate animals by museum faculty and students
  - Administrative Reorganization (Hairston writings) 1974-1975 (Box 5)
  - Animal Care
    - Census of Lab Vertebrates 1965-1979 (Box 5)
    - ULAM (Unit for Laboratory Animal Medicine) 1965-1978 (Box 5)
    - Animal Welfare Act 1960-1978 (Box 5)
    - UCUCA (University Commission on Use and Care of Animals) Correspondence 1987-1993 (Box 5)
    - ULAM Reports and Memos 1983-1993 (Box 5)
    - Inter-departmental Correspondence 1983-1992 (Box 5)
  - Bailey, Dr. Reeve M. (curator) Memo File 1982-1990 (Box 5)
  - Budget Information
    - "The Finances of the Museum of Zoology," 1965 (Box 5)
    - Account Summaries 1972-1976 (Box 5)
  - Budgets and Salaries 1925/25-1949/50 (Folder Bimu/450)
  - Clippings 1993-1999 (Box 5)
  - Compact Storage Units 1975 (Box 5)
  - Directors' Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous 1961-1997 (Box 5)
    - Import/Export Procedures 1971-1981 (Box 5)
    - Sam Krimm 1973-1974 (Box 5)
    - Bland Leverett 1975-1979 (Box 5)
    - Robert Ledbetter 1978-1979 (Box 5)
  - Directors' Memos
    - 1977-1980 (Box 5)
    - 1982 (Box 5)
    - 1983 (Box 5)
    - 1984 (Box 5)
    - 1985 (Box 5)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 5)
  - Directorship Search
    - Acting Director Information 1971-1981 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence and Memos 1979-1982, 2 folders
  - Directories, Museum of Zoology
    - Interoffice Publications 1961-1982 (Box 5)
    - Staff Records Office/University Publication Office 1967-1979 (Box 5)
  - DRDA (Division of Research Development and Administration) Quarterly Reports of zoology research grants 1979 (Box 5)
  - Faculty Work Load (DBS, Division of Biological Sciences) 1972-1978 (Box 5)
  - Faculty Search 1972-1980 (Box 5)
  - Future of the UMMZ 1993-1994 (Box 5)
  - GSRA (Graduate Student Research Assistant) Information 1958-1991 (Box 5)
  - Historical 1937-1993, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Mechanical Drawings of Ruthven Building 1964-1990 (Box 5)
  - Mexican Collecting Permits Correspondence 1966-1971 (Box 6)
  - NSF Proposal (Nelson G. Hairston) 1968-1973 (Box 6)
  - Ottawa National Forest Threatened and Endangered Species 1974 (Box 6)
  - Private Support for Museum Research 1973-1975 (Box 6)
  - Public Service Database Survey 1988 (Box 6)
  - Publications List 1980-1990 (Box 6)
  - Registration and Enrollment Figures (DBS and Dept. of Zoology) 1945-1980 (Box 6)
  - Reports
    - "Grants for Research and Graduate Training in Systematic and Evolutionary Biology," May 1970 (Box 6)
    - "Report to the Director, Museum of Zoology Fund Raising Number 1," November 1979 (Box 6)
    - "A Report from the Director," October 1994 (Box 6)
    - "Special Report to Dean Edie N. Goldenberg," June 1997 (Box 6)
  - Reunion of Ph.Ds from 1961-1971, 1991 (Box 6)
  - Ruthven Professorship and Curatorship 1974-1978 (Box 6)
  - Salary Levels 1956-1961 (Box 6)
  - SARR (Subcommittee Assigned to Review Rackham)
    - Memos and Correspondence 1984 (Box 6)
    - William R. Dawson File (Committee Chair) 1984 (Box 6)
  - Scholarship Awards 1975-1984, 1988-1989, 11 folders (Box 6)
  - Seminars 1979-1989 (Box 7)
  - Space Analysis
    - Departmental Space Inventory Surveys 1981-1989 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence and Memos 1966-1988 (Box 7)
  - Threatened and Endangered Species Survey 1977 (Box 7)
  - Tso-Hsin Cheng Visit 1980-1981 (Box 7)
  - Visiting Professors
    - Bruce Wallace Correspondence 1974-1976 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1974-1976 (Box 7)
  - Visiting Scientist Program 1978-1988 (Box 7)
  - Walker, Charles F. Replacement Documentation 1970-1974 (Box 7)
- Staff Meeting Minutes 1976-1992
  The Staff Meeting Minutes (1.2 linear feet) are arranged chronologically and provide a wealth of information about the daily operations and issues concerning the Museum of Zoology. This is a great place to find insight into the museum itself and the wider role it plays within the Division of Biological Science, the College of Literature Science and the Arts, and the university. Early meeting minutes consist mainly of the director's handwritten agendas and notes from the weekly meetings. Starting in 1981, however, the meetings moved to a monthly format and the prepared agendas and staff packets became more detailed and extensive.
  - 1975-1976 (Box 7)
  - 1976-1977 (Box 7)
  - 1977-1978 (Box 7)
  - 1978-1979 (Box 7)
  - 1979-1980 (Box 7)
  - 1980-1981 (Box 7)
  - 1981-1982 (Box 7)
  - 1982-1983 (Box 7)
  - 1983-1984 (Box 7)
  - 1984-1985 (Box 7)
  - 1985-1986 (Box 7)
  - 1986-1987 (Box 8)
  - 1987-1988 (Box 8)
  - 1988-1989 (Box 8)
  - 1989-1990 (Box 8)
  - 1990-1991 (Box 8)
  - 1991-1992 (Box 8)
Related Material
Researchers should be aware that several other collections at the Bentley Library contain material related to the Museum of Zoology. In addition to the University of Michigan Museums collection, the following personal collections should be consulted: Marston Bates, Jacob Ellsworth Reighard, Alexander Grant Ruthven, Joseph B. Steere, and Josselyn Van Tyne.